<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<chapter>
<section niv='1'><title>Using Tcl Interface</title>

<section niv='2'><title>Script Launch</title>
<p>All functionalities of the &tool; platform can be accessed with the <f>avt_shell</f> Tcl scripting interface.
<f>avt_shell</f> can be used the same way as any <f>.tcl</f> script. </p>
<p><f>avt_shell</f> can be used in interactive mode or in script mode. In interactive mode, it is invoked as follow:</p>  
<code>
<cl>&gt; avt_shell</cl>
</code>
<p>In script mode, the first line of the script file should look like:</p>
<code>
<cl>#!/usr/bin/env avt_shell</cl>
</code>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Tools Configuration</title>
<p>The configuration of all the timing tools of the &tool; platform is done in the same way, by the mean
of configuration variables. The value given to the variable determines the specific behavior of the
tool. When using the Tcl interface, the setting of the values for the configuration variables can be done
in two ways:</p>
<list>
<item>In the special file <f>avttools.conf</f> in the working directory, with the syntax <f>variable = value</f>. Old way, 
not recommended. Only kept for backward compatibilty.</item>
<item>In the <f>avt_shell</f> script, through the <f>avt_config</f> function, taking the variable
for first parameter and its affected value for second parameter (<f>avt_config variable value).</f></item>
</list>
<p>There is a precedence of the values set in the <f>avttools.conf</f> file on the values set in the 
<f>avt_shell script</f>.</p>
</section>


<section niv='2'><title>Functions</title>
<p>Here is a list of the families of Tcl functions that can be found within the <f>avt_shell</f> interface. 
For more information, see &tool; Reference Guide.</p>

<glossary>
<row><article>General</article><def>Global configuration, file loading, netlist manipulation, statistics</def></row>
<row><article>INF Configuration</article><def>Configuration though the INF functions</def></row>
<row><article>HDL Construction</article><def>Automatic or manual generation of the VHDL/Verilog</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>


<section niv='2'><title>INF and SDC Configuration</title>
<p>For tool configuration needing more than the specification of a simple value (as it is done through the
<f>avt_config</f> function), &tool; uses the INF mechanism, which is a set of Tcl configuration functions.</p>
<p>SDC commands are grouped together with the INF functions and share the same mechanisms.</p>
<p>All INF functions begin with the <f>inf_</f> prefix, except of the SDC commands, which respect their standard naming.</p> 

<p>Within a Tcl script, the target sub-circuit must be defined before using INF or SDC commands. Following example is 
given for a sub-circuit named <f>my_design</f>.</p> 
<code>
<cl>inf_SetFigureName my_design</cl>
<cl> </cl>
<cl>set_case_analysis 1 reset</cl>
<cl>inf_DefineMutex muxup {i0 i1 i2}</cl>
</code>

<p>It is possible to check the INF and SDC functions by driving a <f>.inf</f> file.
Adding the line:</p>
<code>
<cl>inf_Drive my_design</cl>
</code>
<p>at the end of the previous Tcl script generates the <f>my_design.inf</f> file. Each INF and SDC function has 
a corresponding section in this file (see &tool; Reference Guide).</p>
</section>

</section></chapter>
