<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<chapter>
<section niv='1'><title>Overview</title>

<section niv='2'><title>Static Timing Analysis</title>
<p>The advent of semiconductor fabrication technologies now allows high performance in complex 
integrated circuits.</p> 
<p>With the increasing complexity of these circuits, static timing analysis (STA) 
has revealed itself as the only feasible method ensuring that expected performances are 
actually obtained.</p>
<p>In addition, signal integrity (SI) issues due to crosstalk play a crucial role in 
performance and reliability of these systems, and must be taken into account during 
the timing analysis.</p>
<p>However, performance achievement not only lies in fabrication technologies, but also 
in the way circuits are designed. Very high performance designs are obtained with semi or 
full-custom designs techniques.</p>
<p>The &tool; platform provides advanced STA and SI solutions at transistor level. It has 
been built-up in order to allow engineers to ensure complete timing and SI coverage on their digital 
custom designs, as well as IP-reuse through timing abstraction. </p>
<p>Furthermore, hierarchy handling through transparent timing views allows full-chip 
verification, with virtually no limit of capacity in design size.</p>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Signal Integrity Analysis </title>
<p>&tool; crosstalk engine is coupled with static timing analysis (STA) engine and is based 
upon a multi-switching windows refinement algorithm.</p>
<p>Crosstalk effects are then fully handled in timing checks. Precise delay update is done thanks 
to current source models for gate, and non-linear charge transfer models for effective wire load 
computation.</p>
<p>Detailed SI report provides:</p>
<list>
<item>Delta-delays in gates and interconnects</item>
<item>Effective noise contribution of each aggressor</item>
<item>Overshoot and undershoot peaks, together with sensitivity of the fan-out gates</item>
<item>Statistical noise classification allowing Engineering Change Orders</item>
</list>
<p>The graphical user interface (GUI) allows easy execution of the crosstalk analysis.</p>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Applications</title>
<p>&tool; can be used on a wide range of ICs, such as Micro-Processors, Micro-Controllers, 
Memory Controllers, Custom IPs or Standard-Cell Libraries (Arithmetic Units, Data-Paths...). It 
provides the following benefits:</p>
<p>Timing sign-off</p>
<list>
<item>Digital custom macros STA sign-off</item>
<item>Full-chip STA sign-off</item>
</list>
<p>Signal Integrity sign-off</p>
<list>
<item>Digital custom macros crosstalk analysis</item>
<item>Full-chip crosstalk analysis</item>
</list>
<p>Design and debug</p>
<list>
<item>Circuit timing analysis during design phase</item>
<item>Early detection of timing bottlenecks</item>
</list>
<p>IP Reuse (.lib files generation)</p>
<list>
<item>Digital custom macros characterization</item>
<item>Standard cells re-characterization</item>
</list>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Key Features</title>
<p>&tool; provides the following features:</p>
<list>
<item>Vector-free fast simulation engine, accuracy within 5% of SPICE</item>
<item>Current Source Modeling (CSM) of drivers, AWE modeling of interconnects</item>
<item>SPICE, VHDL or VERILOG netlist support, SPICE, SPEF or DSPF parasitics support, BSIM3 and BSIM4 support</item>
<item>Design-style support: latch-based, domino logic, barrel shifters, multipliers</item>
<item>Advanced timing checks: cycle sharing, cycle stealing, multicycle paths</item>
<item>Full-Chip analysis through transparent hierarchy</item>
<item>Cross corner analysis</item>
<item>STA and SI coupled analysis</item>
<item>Non-linear noise models</item>
<item>Statistical noise classification</item>
<item>GUI and Tcl interface</item>
<item>Critical path automatic spice deck</item>
<item>SDC timing constraints</item>
</list>
</section>

</section>
</chapter>


