<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<chapter>
<section niv='1'><title>Glossary</title>

<section niv='2'><title>Logical Description</title>
<glossary>
<row><article>Subcircuit</article><def>Base object of a hierarchical description. The subcircuit is defined by its components,
which may be elementary objects (transistors, resistances, capacitances...) or instances of other subcircuits.</def></row>
<row><article>Cell</article><def>Predefined subcircuit, only containing elementary objects, that may be selected and arranged to create custom or semi-custom integrated circuit. </def></row>
<row><article>Instance</article><def>Call of a subcircuit in a specific context</def></row>
<row><article>(Logical) Signal</article><def>Object carrying logical information between instances or elementary objects</def></row>
<row><article>Connector</article><def>Object carrying the logical information of a signal through the interface of an instance.</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Physical Description</title>
<glossary>
<row><article>RC network</article><def>Connected set of R and C devices</def></row>
<row><article>Net</article><def>Individual RC network linked to a logical signal. The RC network
presents a resistive path between connectors of connected instances. Capacitances are substrate or coupling ones.</def></row>
<row><article>Node</article><def>Single point in a RC network</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Timing Description</title>
<glossary>
<row><article>(Timing) Signal</article><def>Point of the circuit where the timing propagation of the logical information is 
measured. Whereas the logical signal is linked to a net, the timing signal is linked to a node. 
Indeed, as propagation delays in RC networks must be taken into account, it is necessary to measure the 
timing propagation of the logical information on several points of the net. The methodology in &tool; is to associate 
a timing signal with each terminal node of a net. As a result, several timing signals may exist where only one 
logical signal exist.</def></row>
<row><article>Event</article><def>Rising or falling logical transition on a timing signal</def></row>
<row><article>Reference point</article><def>Timing signal where timing checks must be performed: input or output 
connectors, latch, precharge, latch or precharge commands.</def></row>
<row><article>Path</article><def>List of timing signals, from reference point to reference point, 
through which logical information is carried</def></row>
<row><article>Break point</article><def>User defined reference point</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>

<imgsize namehtml="terminology.gif" namepdf="terminology.gif" hpdf="300pt"/>
</section>
</chapter>
