<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<glossary>
<row type="split"><article><index>avtAnnotationPreserveExistingParasitics</index></article><def>
<glossary width='small'>
<row><article><f>yes</f></article><def>Existing parasitics on nets annotated in a DSPF/SPEF file won't 
be overridden by the parasitics in the DSPF/SPEF file. The DSPF/SPEF information will rather be added to the existing ones.  </def></row>
<row><article><f>no</f></article><def>Default</def></row>
</glossary>
</def></row>

<row type='split'><article><index>avtAnnotationDeviceConnectorSetting</index></article><def>
<glossary width='small'>
<row><article><f>&lt;string&gt;</f></article><def>Overrides the internal tool known device connector names used in DSPF/SPEF annotation.
The string must contain 10 items in the following order: transistor source name, transistor gate name, transistor drain name, transistor bulk name,
resistor positive connector, resistor negative connector, capacitor positive connector, capacitor negative connector,
diode positive connector, diode negative connector. By default, the tool knows of "s g d b 1 2 1 2 1 2" and "s g d b pos neg 1 2 1 2".
<p>Example:</p>
<p><f>avt_config avtAnnotationDeviceConnectorSetting "src gate drn blk 1 2 1 2 1 2"</f></p>
</def></row>
</glossary>
</def></row>

<row type='split'><article><index>avtSpiDspfBuildPower</index></article><def>
<glossary width='small'>
<row><article><f>yes</f></article><def>Only used for DSPF annotation. When creating a figure from 
DSPF information, use the avtGlobalVddName, avtGlobalVssName, avtVddName and avtVssName to detect power 
connections on the instance, so they are created on the boundary of it instead of 
being merged with all unknown connectors.</def></row>
<row><article><f>no</f></article><def></def></row>
</glossary>
</def></row>

<row type='split'><article><index>avtSpiDspfLinkExternal</index></article><def>
<glossary width='small'>
<row><article><f>yes</f></article><def>Only used for DSPF annotation. When an external connector is not 
connected to anything, and if there is an internal signal with the same name, then the connector is assumed to be on 
this signal.</def></row>
<row><article><f>no</f></article><def></def></row>
</glossary>
</def></row>

<row type='split'><article><index>avtSpiPinDspfOrder</index></article><def>
<glossary width='small'>
<row><article><f>yes</f></article><def>Only used for DSPF annotation. Order of connector of an instance is 
the one described in the DSPF instead of the one described for the instance interface.</def></row>
<row><article><f>no</f></article><def></def></row>
</glossary>
</def></row>
</glossary>
