
<chapter>
<section niv='1'><title>Theory Understanding</title>

<section niv='2'><title>Principles</title>
<p>The way &tool; performs timing analysis of integrated circuits can be described in two main steps. The 
first step is the generation of a Unified Timing Database (UTD) from the design entry (left-hand side of the
following diagram). The second step is the exploitation of the database, in order to perform Static 
Timing Analysis, Signal Integrity Analysis, and Timing abstraction (right-hand side of the
following diagram).</p>
<imgsize xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" namehtml="hitas_flow.gif" namepdf="hitas_flow.svg"/>
<p>The timing database represents the intrinsic timing characteristics of the design, 
for a given corner, or multi-corner configuration (processes, voltages and temperatures). 
Those characteristics are such as gate timing arcs, gate and interconnect delay models, timing paths.</p>
</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Timing Database Generation</title>

<section niv='3'><title>MOS Characterization</title>
<p>At transistor-level, &tool; works either on a flat transistor netlist obtained by a standard extractor, or on a hierarchical netlist,
together with the transistor description of the leaf cells. In the last case, &tool; flattens the netlist to 
the transistor level.</p>

<p>The first phase of the database generation consists in the electrical characterization of the 
MOS transistors building up the design. The process of characterization is the reduction and 
optimization of the generic BSIM equations for each instance of a transistor, with regard to local 
and global parameters.</p>
<p>The local parameters are the instance-specific parameters, such as length (L), 
width (W), geometry (NF), stress effect (SA, SB, SD), well proximity effect (MULU0, DELVT0),
local drain/source resistances (NRD, NRS) or local power supply voltage value.</p> 
<p>The global parameters are the Process, Voltage (nominal) and Temperature conditions. </p>
<p>For given PVT conditions, each transistor is then associated with an instance-specific electrical model, 
which in turn contains instance-specific optimized equations:</p>
<list>
<item>Ids = f (Vgs, Vds)</item>
<item>Qd = f (Vgs, Vds)</item>
</list>
<p>The model is only valid for the transistor referring to it. However, in order to save memory, a 
sharing mechanism allows transistors that have identical (or close) instance-specific 
parameters to refer to the same electrical model. Note that a transistor may be characterized for several 
PVT conditions, and then may be associated to several models.</p>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Netlist Disassembly</title>
<p>The second phase of the database generation consists in partitioning the transistor netlist. This phase 
uses a procedure called circuit disassembly in order to automatically extract an oriented gate netlist from 
the transistor netlist, using a strict minimum of a priori knowledge of the circuit structures. </p>

<p>The starting point of the partitioning strategy is the identification of the nodes on which to build 
a sub-network. The innovation of &tool; disassembly is to build sub-networks between which there is no 
charge transfer. Therefore, the frontier of a sub-network is the set of nodes that control
the gates (insulating polysilicon) of its transistors. A sub-network 
is then extracted for all the nodes in the netlist that control at less one transistor gate,
by following source-drain connections.</p>

<p>The extracted sub-networks are called cones. The construction of a cone on a node N consists in 
identifying all the current paths between the node N and a voltage source (Vdd or Vss), as illustrated 
in the following diagram.</p>

<imgsize xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" namehtml="partitioning.gif" namepdf="partitioning.svg"/>

<p>Each cone has a unique output and a certain number of inputs: the nodes controlling the gates of 
the cone's transistors.</p>

<p>The tool also automatically identifies the memory elements such as memory-cells, latches, pre-charged nodes.</p>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Timing Arcs</title>
<p>The third phase consists of mapping a timing graph on the cone netlist obtained through the disassembly 
phase (partitioning phase). Timing graph also includes RC networks. The timing graph is defined as follow: 
edges are rising or falling events (logic transitions) on an input or output of a cone. Arcs are possible 
causality relations between events. Causality relations are also called timing arcs.</p>

<imgsize xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" namehtml="timing_arcs.gif" namepdf="timing_arcs.svg"/>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Timing Models</title>
<p>The fourth phase consists of the valuation of the timing arcs. A major innovation in &tool; methodology 
is the valuation of the timing arcs by delay models.</p>
<p>When a timing arc refers to a cone, it is associated with analytical current source models (CSM), which enable to compute the effective delay for any input slope or output load
(CSM present the significant advantage to be independent from input slope and output load). 
It ensures high precision in slope propagation and crosstalk analysis (where effective load 
can change during analysis).</p>
<p>The current source models are based on analytical equations, and take into account the following factors:</p>
<list>
<item>The input slope, modeled as a non-linear curve</item>
<item>The output load, modeled as a pi-network</item>
<item>The transient short circuit current during the commutation of a gate</item>
</list>
<p>When a timing arc refers to an RC network, it is associated with the RC network. Effective delay is computed with the AWE algorithm for any input slope or output load.</p>  

</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Timing Paths</title>
<p>The last phase consists of the creation of all the timing paths: the successive timing arcs 
between connectors and memory elements are merged to create timing paths. All
the possible timing paths in the design are saved into the database.</p>
</section>



</section>

<section niv='2'><title>Timing Database Analysis</title>

<section niv='3'><title>Database Analysis Flow</title>
<p>The diagram below presents the set of functionalities of the &tool; platform, for complete timing and
SI analysis, allowing to performing frequency optimization and violations repairs.</p>
<imgsize xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" namehtml="UTD_analysis.gif" namepdf="UTD_analysis.svg"/>
<glossary>
<row><article>Timing Constraints</article> <def>Input connectors arrival times, output connectors departure times, clocks specifications</def></row>
<row><article>STA and SI</article> <def>STA is optionally coupled with the SI analysis</def></row>
<row><article>Path Analysis</article> <def>ECO to repair violations or optimize frequencies</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Static Timing Analysis </title>
<p>The static timing analyzer engine of &tool; calculates setup and hold slacks for all reference points in a circuit 
(output connectors, latch data inputs, latch commands, and precharged nodes). The algorithm is based upon the propagation 
of switching windows throughout the design. The engine needs the specification 
of the external clocks and the arrival times of the input connectors (which define  
switching windows). Together with the timing database,
the tool propagates the switching windows and the clocks throughout the circuit, 
in order to obtain switching windows for the points which require verification (the reference points).</p>
<p>The tool calculates setup and hold slacks for each of the reference points by comparing the switching 
windows obtained at the point with the propagated clocks according to specific timing checks. 
Any violation of the timing checks translates into a negative value calculated for the setup or hold slacks.</p>
</section>


<section niv='3'><title>Crosstalk Analysis</title>
<p>Coupling capacitances influence depends on the relative activity on nets. The crosstalk analysis 
engine should be used to calculate the timing information based upon relative net activity using the 
current-source models from the timing database.</p>

<p>From the switching windows obtained through the static timing analysis, it is possible to determine whether two capacitance-coupled nets
may present simultaneous switching. If this occurs, the mutual influence between the nets is modeled by altering 
the effective value of the coupling capacitance in accordance with the relative slope values of the signals propagated on the two nets. 
When the effective value of a capacitance on a net is changed, the associated propagation delay of its driver must be reevaluated. 
Even the altering of a single propagation delay leads to switching window changes on all subsequent nets. As a result, 
a new static timing analysis must be performed on the circuit, potentially leading to the detection of new aggression. 
This loop is then repeated until no new simultaneous switching is detected.</p>

<p>The crosstalk analysis engine calculates all propagation delays for all the instances of a subcircuit, according to their context. 
When all of these delays are computed, setup and hold margins for each of the reference points are calculated 
and verified, as for the static timing analysis. In addition, the crosstalk analysis engine generates a report file 
for the circuit containing: details of aggression, the modification of delays according to the detailed 
behavior of aggressors, together with an evaluation of peak noise voltage.</p>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Path Searching</title>
<p>Path searching is done between reference points, i.e. input and output connectors, latch data inputs, latch commands, and precharged nodes. The 
information from the static timing analysis are taken into account in order to determine if paths can go through
the latches that may have a transparent behavior.</p> 
<p>Together with the propagated clocks, the switching windows define the state of the latches and precharged nodes
at the arrival of the input data. If the latch or precharged node is in a transparent state, then the path goes 
through it.</p>
</section>

<section niv='3'><title>Timing Abstraction</title>
<p>The timing abstraction engine generates timing models of macro-cells and IP-cores, 
consisting of lookup tables for all timing paths.  
In a timing model, timing arcs are given as constraints with respect to interface connectors of the block to be abstracted. </p>

<p>Each instantiation context of a timing model, in terms of input slope and output load, will be different. 
Lookup tables are therefore necessary for each situation to be handled. A lookup table is generated for each of timing 
paths and timing constraints. Timing models are given in Cadence TLF3/4 format or in Synopsys Liberty format.</p>
</section>

</section>

</section></chapter>
