<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<section niv='3'><title>Description</title>

<p>The <f>.inf</f> file is an ASCII file with different sections. Blank lines, lines starting with '#' or any
character between '/*' and '*/' are considered as comments. Most of the sections, except the header,
are defined with a section name and the information related to this section are enclosed with <f>Begin</f>
and <f>End;</f>. The syntax for each section depends on the section itself. The sections are not
depending on each other so they can be declared out of order and several times.</p>
<p>The syntax is case insensitive for the keywords. The signal names can be given without
quotes but to enable the use of signal names with special characters or unfortunately matching a
keyword, they are required.</p>
<p>It is also possible to use units. For timing values with
no specified unit, the Pico-second will be used. Valid units are: ps, ns, ms.
For the capacitance values with no unit is specified, the Femto-farad will be used.
Valid units are: pf, ff.
</p>
<p>The information file gives information for the abstraction, database construction and static timing analysis
tools. The information file name does not need to be related to a subcircuit name. In fact, the
first token that should be set in the information file is "name" followed by the subcircuit name
the information are given for. If this information is not given, the information file parser will guess
the name of the subcircuit from the file name.</p>

<p>For a subcircuit, several information files can be given. They will be loaded in a particular
order and the information will be merged. Actually, there are 2 different information files
that can be generated by our tools and loaded, by default, with the following precedence:</p>

<section niv='4'><title>SDC input file</title>
<p>The SDC command will be translated in the appropriate information file sections.</p>
</section>

<section niv='4'><title>User-defined INF file</title>
<p>The order of loading and the files to load can be set by modifying the variable
<f>avtReadInformationFile</f>. The files are separated by commas and the special character
'$' will be replaced by the subcircuit name. Regular expressions can be used there to handle
more complicated naming. Its default value is <f>$.spice.inf,$.sdc.inf,$.inf</f>. The '\' before
the '.' simply indicates to the regular expression matching algorithm not to interpret '.' as any
characters but as the character '.'. The names are from the less priority to the more priority.
If the value is set to <f>no</f>, no information file will be loaded.</p>
</section>

</section>
