<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<section niv='3'><title>Timing Abstraction Directives</title>

<section niv='4'><title>Parameterization of Lookup Tables</title>

<p>Lookup tables defined for timing paths depend
on input slopes and output capacitances. The SLOPEIN and CAPAOUT sections provide various means
for specifying the ranges of slopes and capacitances applied on external connectors.
Ranges can be set for selected connectors, but a default range can also be given, using the
keyword 'default'.
Ranges can be set by enumeration, using the syntax:</p>
<code>signal: (slope_0, slope_1, ... , slope_n);</code>
<p>Ranges can also be set by specifying a lower bound,  an upper bound, and a step, using the syntax:</p>
<code>signal: (lower_bound: upper_bound: step);</code> 
</section>

<section niv='4'><title>SLOPEIN</title>

<p>The SLOPEIN section describes the slopes to be applied on input connectors. 
Slopes are given in pico-seconds.</p>
<code>
<cl>SLOPEIN</cl>
<cl>BEGIN</cl>
<cl>    sig1: (100, 400, 900, 1500, 2200, 3000);</cl>
<cl>    sig2: (100: 1000: 100);</cl>
<cl>    default: (100, 400, 900, 1500, 2200, 3000);</cl>
<cl>    ...</cl>
<cl>END;</cl>
</code>
</section>

<section niv='4'><title>CAPAOUT</title>

<p>The CAPAOUT section describes the capacitances to be applied on output connectors.
To specify capacitances, a scaling factor is available. The range of capacitance
can be given for specific length and width of transistors. The capacitances really applied
on the connector are then scaled by the ratio between the given length and width, and the characteristic
length and width of the transistors of the cell driving the pin.
Capacitances are given in Femto-farads, lengths are given microns.
</p>

<code>
<cl>CAPAOUT</cl>
<cl>BEGIN</cl>
<cl>    sig1: (0.7, 80.5, 190.0, 300.5); </cl>
<cl>    sig2: (0: 250: 25);</cl>
<cl>    default: (0.3, 38.5, 147.0, 311.5) L=0.18 W=0.6;</cl>
<cl>    ...</cl>
<cl>END;</cl>
</code>
</section>


<section niv='4'><title>CLOCK CONNECTORS</title>

<p>Clocks must be declared in the information file in order to compute setup and hold constraints. These clocks are specified in the CLOCK CONNECTORS section.</p>
<code>
<cl>CLOCK CONNECTORS</cl>
<cl>BEGIN</cl>
<cl>    sig1;</cl>
<cl>    sig2;</cl>
<cl>    ...</cl>
<cl>END;</cl>
</code>
</section>
</section>
