<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<section niv='2'><title>Transistor Netlist Recognition </title>

<p> The FCL API allows the user to use GNS actions to generate all the transistor netlist markings 
of the FCL transistor recognition module.  </p>

<section niv='2'><title>Available Markings</title>
<p>The markings available for the signals are the following ones:</p>
<glossary>
<row type='split'><article>NET_LATCH</article><def>Signal corresponds to a latch memory-point.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_FLIPFLOP</article><def>Signal corresponds to a flip-flop memory-point.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_MASTER</article><def>Signal corresponds to the master memory-point of a flip-flop.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_SLAVE</article><def>Signal corresponds to the slave memory-point of a flip-flop.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_MEMSYM</article><def>Signal corresponds to one side of a symmetric memory.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_RS</article><def>Signal corresponds to one side of an RS bistable.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_VDD</article><def>Signal corresponds to an alimentation.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_VSS</article><def>Signal corresponds to ground.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_BLOCKER</article><def>No branch of a cone (see man &MIN;) can go through the signal.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_STOP</article><def>Cannot exploit logic beyond this point for functional analysis in the disassembler. </def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_BYPASS</article><def>Signal cannot appear in a timing path. </def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_MATCHNAME</article><def>The signal is only matched if the name in the pattern to recognize and the name in the source netlist are identical.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>NET_SENSITIVE</article><def>Marks the signal as a particularly sensitive signal. If a timed behavioral model of this signal is produced then the most precise (but cumbersome) model will be generated.</def></row>
</glossary>

<p>The markings available for the transistors are the following ones:</p>
<glossary>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_BLEEDER</article><def>Transistor corresponds to a bleeder.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_FEEDBACK</article><def>Transistor corresponds to a feedback transistor of a memory-point.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_COMMAND</article><def>Transistor corresponds to a command transistor of a memory-point, i.e driven by command signal.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_NOT_FUNCTIONAL</article><def>Transistor should be ignored when calculating gate functionality.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_BLOCKER</article><def>No branch of a cone  can contain this transistor unless it is the first transistor of the branch.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_UNUSED</article><def>No branch of a cone can contain this transistor.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_SHORT</article><def>The transistor is considered short-circuited, the gate signal no longer contributes to the list of inputs.</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_MATCHSIZE</article><def>The transistor is only matched if the dimensions correspond exactly or to within a given tolerance (see FCL configuration).</def></row>
<row type='split'><article>TRANS_SHARE</article><def>The transistor can be matched by several patterns.</def></row>
</glossary>
</section>

&fcl_API;

</section>
